Hi, this is Robert Scheer with another
edition of Scheer Intelligence and I'm
bringing back an old guest, one of the
people I've had I don't know
a number of times and
it's just somebody I have such enormous
admiration for
and
and he's gone through John Kiriakou. Let
me just cut to the chase.
John, when did you you were recruited
out of what? George Washington
University to
Right.
go work for the CIA. What year was that?
I was recruited in 1989 and I started
working for the CIA in
the first week of January of 1990.
And you stayed there until when?
I left in
the spring of 2004.
2004, so that's what? 15 years, 14
years?
Yeah, about 14 and a half years.
Yeah, and the you had and you learned
Arabic.
I did. They taught me Arabic.
And
and amazingly enough,
the reason I wanted to talk to you
I I teach at the University of Southern
California and I showed
the
film The Report which I think is
excellent and
it's on the the Senate Intelligence
Committee's
report on torture.
Yes.
And Dianne Feinstein who was the chair
of that committee over with Republican
objection but she was the head of the
committee and the Democrats controlled
it and they did this study
where did the torture come from? What
was it all about? And they actually
theoretically had the cooperation of the
CIA.
And they came up with an a view I know I
put it in contrast to that the Hollywood
movie Zero Dark Thirty which said that
torture somehow worked and got us
help the US capture Bin Laden and then
kill him
and so forth and none of that turned out
to be true. And but the fact of the
matter is I can't refer listeners to the
torture report that they paid for. How
many pages was it?
The report itself was about 5,500 pages
long.
Yeah, and when did it come out?
It came out in December 2014.
Okay. So it's almost a decade ago and
the only part that was released was the
introduction heavily redacted.
The report itself may not even exist
anymore. I don't know. There were a
couple of copies, right? And what
happened to it?
Yeah, that's that's really a very
important issue that I think most
Americans either don't know or have
forgotten about. The CIA only produced
six or seven issues or copies, I should
say, of the of the full report. What we
saw was a heavily redacted version of
the executive summary of the report,
which was about 500 pages.
But the report itself
was owned by the CIA. The CIA maintained
ownership and control, final word, over
the actual report itself. So there there
was a report in the New York Times
about 3 years after
the report was was finally written
saying that the CIA was going to begin
taking back the copies that had gone to
places like the Executive Office of the
President, the Office of the Vice
President, the Senate and House
Intelligence Committees,
etc. And they were going to begin
destroying them.
Well, we don't know if that ever
happened.
So it may exist, it may not exist. We
just don't know. What we do know is that
it probably will never be declassified.
So,
the reason this is so critical is
without getting into any conspiracy
theories, although conspiracy theory is
kind of a way of just alluding to
hypothesis
that either have been explored or have
not or can be documented or not, but the
fact of the matter is
the main
evidence that would be available about
what happened on 9/11, how we got into a
war on terror, what Al-Qaeda was all
about, what was his relation to Saudi
Arabia. After all, 15 of the 19
hijackers were Saudi
troops or whatever they were, they're
young men from Saudi Arabia. And just
this week as we're recording this, the
president of the United States
who spoke at the UN about we represent
democracy and just about every other
country in the world is not in Western
Europe or not a former major colonial
power
represents authoritarian
governments whatever they are. And
ironically, it's the same week in which
he said he's going to develop an
alliance with Saudi Arabia to protect
them militarily. So, here's this
self-proclaimed you know great democracy
and we still really don't know the
details of what happened at 9/11 as far
as Saudi Arabia's relationship to they
certainly you know
citizens of Saudi Arabia who were living
there actually uh
15 of the 19 were from there.
Uh none from Iraq.
Uh none from Afghanistan so that we
countries that we invaded. So, that that
you know you would expect that when you
capture people
uh you would learn something about what
they are and then you would have a trial
hopefully a public trial of these
people. That didn't happen.
And you figure into this historic story,
maybe, you know, certainly one of the
most the major one of the three or four
most important events in American
history, changed a whole nature of our
government to national security state,
solidified it. You were then in the CIA,
you were an Arabic speaker, and let's
just begin with that. You were involved
in the first major capture of somebody
who was said at the time to be uh the
number three person in Al-Qaeda. And and
and the movie The Report deals with the
interrogation of that person. And the
reason I felt some urgency in doing this
is in my class that I was teaching and I
showed The Report, I was shocked that
it's a class of about, you know, I think
68 students, all very sharp,
great SAT scores, and none of them knew
about this report, and none of them were
really familiar through their high
school or
years of college education about what
had happened, the torture, the torture
program.
That's shocking to me.
yeah, and here's the president of the
United States talks, we are the great
democracy, but we're the great democracy
that did the torture program. You were
there. Let's set this historically.
Yeah.
Just cuz people don't know that story
now, John. Uh tell us what happened. How
did you get the call? Why were you the
person that received this uh prisoner?
And what happened to him?
Right. Well, really, like so many of
these stories, it begins on 9/11. Um
like everybody else in the CIA, I
volunteered that very day to go to
Afghanistan and fight or do whatever was
required of me.
Um I volunteered repeatedly, stressing
that I was I was fluent in the Arabic
language, and certainly they would need
people to carry out these uh these uh
interrogations and interviews and
debriefings
and they just ignored me. Every time I
would I would volunteer, they'd say,
"Thank you very much." and they would
ignore me. Well, it turned out in those
early days immediately after 9/11,
um they they weren't they weren't
interviewing people. They weren't
interrogating anybody. They were killing
them.
And so, finally, I made what really was
an idle threat. I went into the office
of the Deputy Director for
Counterterrorism
who was a friend of mine and I said
I said, "Look, if you don't send me to
Afghanistan right now, I am walking
straight to Exxon with my Arabic and I
am not looking back."
And he said, "Oh, relax, relax. Okay."
And I had been volunteering to him, you
know, for months at that point. And he
said, "Can you go to Pakistan?" I said,
"Yes, when?"
He said, "Tomorrow." I said, "Yes, what
do you want me to do?" He said, "I want
you to be Chief of Counterterrorism
Operations." I said, "Okay, done." And I
walked right over to the travel office
and made a reservation, called my then
girlfriend
This is at uh in Langley. This is at the
CIA.
At the CIA's headquarters, yeah. Told I
called my girlfriend who was also a CIA
officer, told her I was going to
Pakistan the next day. She said, "How
long?" I said, "I don't know, 6 months,
12 months, I don't know."
She said, "Okay, I'll meet you at your
place and help you pack." And the next
day I flew to Pakistan.
So, we began doing counterterrorism
raids very slowly. I had been there
about a week. I'd come up with a
standard operating procedure for taking
down a
suspected safe house and in the first
raid that we did, of course, we
partnered with the FBI because 9/11 was
still an open criminal investigation. We
partnered with Pakistani intelligence
because, after all, it's their country.
And so, um
we broke down the door of of this house
at 2:00 in the morning and and grabbed
two 18-year-olds. Both of them began
crying. One asked if he could call his
mother. It was pathetic.
And it was easy.
And so, about a week later, a friendly
Arab intelligence officer passed me a
slip of paper with an address on it and
he said, "I think this is an Egyptian
Islamic Jihad safe house." I said,
"Great. Thank you." That night, we broke
down the door and grabbed two members of
the Egyptian Islamic Jihad. So, I said,
"You know, this is going pretty well.
But, um
we're going to be here for 50 years if
we're going to be breaking down doors
and grabbing one guy or two guys."
So, I came up with this idea. We had CIA
officers all the way up and down the
Pakistan-Afghanistan
border,
uh in in every little border village,
just sort of standing there with with
binoculars to see if uh there were
Al-Qaeda people trying to cross the
border. So, I said, "I had this idea.
Let's pull all of our guys off the
border.
We'll let Al-Qaeda come into the country
because you know they're going to all go
to the same handful of safe houses. You
know they're going to make a mistake,
probably an electronic mistake, and then
we can raid the house and catch 20, 30,
40 of them at a time." So, we did that
and then started having success.
Well, on the night of uh March uh 22nd,
2002,
we did we carried out 13 simultaneous
raids at 2:00 a.m. And in the course of
those raids, we captured Abu Zubaydah,
who we believed at the time was the
number three in Al-Qaeda. We captured
the commanders of both of Al-Qaeda's
training camps in uh Kandahar and
Helmand provinces in southern
Afghanistan, and we caught dozens upon
dozens of of low-level Al-Qaeda
fighters. Now,
you said something that's important. You
You talked about Guantanamo for a
moment, and I want to tell you about the
first time I heard anything about
Guantanamo. I mean, I knew since I was a
kid that Guantanamo was this American
base that we maintained in Cuba that the
Cubans hated, and that was pretty much
all I knew about it. So, after the Abu
Zubaydah raids, we had captured so many
people that my Pakistani intelligence
counterpart called me one day and said,
"Listen, the jail is full. We just can't
squeeze one more person into the jail.
You're going to have to do something
with all these prisoners."
So, I called CIA headquarters,
the Counterterrorism Center, and I said,
"Rawalpindi jail is full, and the
Pakistanis want us to get these guys
out. What should I do with them?"
And the response was, "Put them on a
C-12 transport plane and send them to
Guantanamo."
And I said, "Guantanamo, Cuba?"
And he said, "Yes."
I said, "Why in the world would we send
them to Cuba?"
And he said, "Oh, we came up with this
idea. We're going to send everybody to
Cuba for a couple of weeks until we can
decide which federal district court to
try them in."
You don't mean You don't mean actually
the country of Cuba. You mean a portion
of Cuba that the US had seized through
its
colonial connection.
Right.
Guantanamo, yeah.
I mean,
but it's in It's in Cuba.
Yeah. Yeah, but was obviously controlled
by the US.
Right. It's US base in Cuba. So,
the idea was to
was to divide them up and try them in
either Boston,
uh, the southern or eastern districts of
New York,
the eastern district of Virginia, or the
federal district of Washington, D.C. I
said, "That's a great idea.
And so we started loading people on onto
plane after plane after plane and sent
them to Guantanamo. In the end we sent
something like 770 people to Guantanamo.
Um, it turned out that the Vice
President at the time, Dick Cheney,
didn't have any intention
of ever allowing any of those people to
go on trial in the United States. And
then later on, of course, Congress acted
and and formally banned the transfer of
any prisoner from Guantanamo to the
United States even to face trial or to
be transferred into a US prison.
So that just never happened.
Uh, and so one of the the prisoners
who's still there is the man you
captured.
Yes, Abu Zubaydah. Abu Zubaydah
And for people who haven't watched it,
I'm trying to encourage people to watch
the the report. Uh,
and Annette Bening is in it. Uh,
help me here with the
movie. It's Adam Driver is the star.
Annette Bening is terrific as as Dianne
Feinstein. I have to tell you I I didn't
watch this film when it first came out
because I was afraid that
you know, it would upset me, it would
make my heart race, it would give me,
you know, PTSD or something. I ended up
watching it on a plane and I couldn't
tear myself away from it. It was so
wonderfully done.
And the point they made though in this
film, which I've heard you make, is that
when you were in charge at that time and
then that you they brought in the FBI
a serious person who knew how to do
interrogation. You actually got the only
useful information that was ever
obtained in that process. And when the
torture guys from the CIA took over and
they excluded the FBI or the FBI pulled
out cuz they wouldn't do torture, They
didn't get any more information and that
prisoner that prisoner without trial uh
who turns out not to have actually been
officially a member of Al-Qaeda is still
in Guantanamo.
Yeah, this is this is a big problem for
a lot of different reasons. Abu Zubaydah
was first taken to a secret uh prison
where he was um
he was interrogated by an FBI officer
named Ali Soufan.
Um Ali Ali was a a terrific uh
translator, an experienced interrogator,
and over the course of many weeks,
something like 6 weeks, he established a
rapport with Abu Zubaydah, a
relationship that allowed them to carry
on a normal human-to-human conversation.
And in the course of that conversation,
Abu Zubaydah gave us
information that we had never been able
to collect before uh at the CIA or at
the FBI. He gave us, for example,
the Al-Qaeda wiring diagram. Now, that
may not sound like a big deal, but I
assure you it's a very big deal because
we knew about Osama bin Laden and Ayman
al-Zawahiri
and we really didn't know anything else.
So, one of the examples that I like to
give of of what I mean by the wiring
diagram
is Ali asked uh Abu Zubaydah,
"If you were going to do an operation in
Düsseldorf,
how would you do that?" And Abu Zubaydah
responded that, "Well, there's this guy
Muhammad and he's at this address and
Muhammad is good at organization and he
has a friend Ahmed and here's Ahmed's
phone number and Ahmed has access to
weapons and uh there's another guy
Abdurrahman. He's Ahmed's cousin. He has
access to explosives. So, then we could
call the Germans and say, 'Listen, you
have a problem in Düsseldorf and here's
the information.' And they could wrap up
that cell. Well, we we didn't know that
these cells existed. We suspected that
they did,
but we didn't have definitive
information, and especially lead
information, as to how to locate and
capture them. Abu Zubaydah gave us that.
Abu Zubaydah also identified to us
Khalid Sheikh Mohammed as the mastermind
of the 9/11 attacks.
We didn't know that name
until Abu Zubaydah gave it to us. We
knew that there was a very bad man out
there somewhere who went by the nom de
guerre Mukhtar.
Mukhtar was the mastermind of what was
called the Bojinka operation. It was a
plan to hijack six 747s from Manila and
fly them into buildings up and down the
West Coast of the United States.
Uh
the the
operation never took place because
a housekeeper stumbled on the plans
while cleaning the apartment of one of
the uh one of the would-be hijackers.
And she called the police, and the
police raided the apartment, and then it
just never happened. So, we knew this
Mukhtar was out there planning terrible
things. We didn't know who he was. Abu
Zubaydah was amazed that we didn't know
that Mukhtar was Khalid Sheikh Mohammed.
And so, once he told us who that was, we
could target Khalid Sheikh Mohammed, and
we ended up capturing him in uh
Rawalpindi, Pakistan, in August of 2002.
And the interesting thing, you said you
didn't know
they didn't know Khalid Sheikh Mohammed,
but he had been a student, I believe, in
North Carolina, an engineering
uh student, and uh actually kind of a
normal
Yes.
uh person.
Lived with an American family when he
was a student in North Carolina.
Somehow had gotten radicalized after uh
that, but was actually knowledgeable
about American culture and so forth.
Oh, yes.
Yeah.
Very much so.
So, and
so you came up with this information
and and then you discovered that
he wasn't actually Abu Zubaydah was not
actually a member of Al-Qaeda.
Right. That that was one of the one of
several surprises for us. He he had
never formally joined Al-Qaeda. He had
never pledged fealty to Osama bin Laden.
He had never sworn an oath.
So, he was not the number three in
Al-Qaeda. He was a bad man. And he did a
lot of work on behalf of Al-Qaeda. But
he was never a member.
Now getting back to to Ali Soufan.
The CIA was jealous frankly at the
progress that Ali was making. And every
day at the end of the day he would write
a cable back to FBI headquarters
recounting the conversation that he had
had that day with Abu Zubaydah. Well,
even post 9/11
the CIA and the FBI hated each other so
intensely
that even their computer systems were
not compatible.
And so Ali is writing these cables back
to headquarters back to FBI headquarters
every day. And the CIA is not seeing
them.
Once in a while the FBI would write a
memo
and send it over to the CIA saying,
"Yeah, we're talking to him. So, here's
a memo."
Well, the CIA was upset. This is a very
serious bureaucratic
kerfuffle between the two organizations.
And so
in late July of 2002 George Tenet who
was the CIA's director at the time went
to President Bush
and asked President Bush to
to turn primacy of the case over to the
CIA to take it away from the FBI and
give it to the CIA.
Why George W. Bush agreed to do that is
something that I don't think we'll ever
understand. He's never talked about it.
It wasn't in the torture report and
George Tenet has never talked about it,
but that's what happened.
And so,
the FBI knew that the CIA was going to
begin torturing him. And so, to protest
that,
the FBI withdrew all of its personnel,
not just from the secret site, but from
the country that the secret site was in.
On August the 2nd, 2002, the CIA began
torturing Abu Zubaydah and he
immediately clammed up. He was so
upset, so angry,
and disgusted when they started
torturing him that he just went silent.
But,
the two
contract psychologists,
uh James Mitchell and Bruce Jessen, to
whom the CIA had paid $108 million to
come up with the torture program, had to
prove that it was working, even if it
wasn't.
And so, what they did is they took all
of the reporting cables that Ali Soufan
had written,
retyped them in the CIA's database,
sent them back to CIA headquarters and
said, "Oh my god, look. We only
waterboarded him one time and look what
he told us.
He gave us the kitchen sink.
He gave us Khalid Sheikh Mohammed. He
gave us the wiring diagram. Somebody
should call the Germans and tell them
they have a problem in Düsseldorf."
Well, after a while,
they had
reported
which you had already done.
No, I I was I was out of it by then.
No, I mean, but the Germans had already
been called by
By the By the FBI.
Yeah.
Yes.
But, what I don't understand, by the
way, there was a movie cuz the the CIA
was very involved in the making of the
Zero Dark
Ferry.
And they violated and there was even a
a report uh uh special prosecutor report
or
about what they did wrong, but they
revealed the identity of Navy SEALs who
had captured Bin Laden, jeopardized
their security a two the
people working on the movie the right
the screenwriter and the director.
Yeah. What happened was
Kathryn Bigelow who was the director
and
executive producer of Zero Dark Thirty
and Mark Boal who was the lead writer
for Zero Dark Thirty
were able to go to the CIA
to receive classified briefings
in violation of the Espionage Act
over a classified mock-up of the Bin
Laden compound.
They based the the movie on what they
had been told in those classified
briefings.
And then when it was all over they were
invited to
an attaboy session in the CIA's
auditorium called the bubble. The
speaker was the CIA director Leon
Panetta
and in his speech Panetta outed the Navy
SEAL
who had killed Bin Laden as well as
several other Navy SEALs. Panetta later
said he didn't realize there were
uncleared people in the audience. That
was nonsense. It was Panetta's office
that had invited them to the event. And
so the CIA's office of public affairs
went back and not just redacted the
names of the SEALs.
But they redacted
27 lines of otherwise classified
information. Again, that was in
violation of the Espionage Act, but
there was never any price to pay and to
make matters worse
to thank the CIA analysts for giving
them classified information for their
movie
Boal and Bigelow
sent tickets to the to the movie's
premiere in West Hollywood
and uh
and for the people who couldn't make it
to the premiere bought them watches.
If you can imagine anything so corrupt
taking place at the CIA. It's it's just
even in retrospect it's crazy to me.
And in the Inspector General's report
they pointed out there was even chats
about who would play Padilla, who would
play other people. And and I have to
point out cuz I didn't do it in the
introduction. You refused to participate
in the torture program or be trained for
it. They asked you to do it. And you
became a critic of the program after
leaving the CIA. And you are the only
person who has served time for being
having any connection with the CIA and
torture program. Not that you tortured
anyone, but because you were accused of
having revealed some and then you served
just about 2 years
Yes.
in prison.
That's right.
Are you going to tell
what's funny? When when I got out of
prison the first interview that I gave
was to the BBC
Hard Talk, I think is what it's it's a
it's a kind of a hard-hitting
mean-spirited talk show. And the host
kept trying to provoke me.
And he said finally, "Well, you're not
showing any remorse for the crime that
you committed." And I said, "No, because
I have no remorse. It's not a crime to
reveal a crime. The crime was committed
by the CIA. The crime was committed by
the torturers. I'll never apologize for
what I did." I said, "John McCain got up
on the floor of the United States Senate
to thank me for providing a public
service to the American people. I'm glad
that I did what I did."
John McCain who had been tortured
who had been tortured, that's right. And
talking to the New York Times and and
the and ABC News is is not espionage.
Sorry, it's just not.
Well, it's good to know that despite
prison and being the only person
who and the irony of it, the only person
who served time for the torture program
is the person who was accused of having
exposed it.
Uh so much for respect for the truth. I
just want to bring up one little
footnote in this connection. Before
9/11, there was a good Hollywood movie
made about the terrorism called The
Siege with Denzel Washington.
All right.
I right. I happen to have a bit part cuz
our show that actually was done for KCRW
that we're doing this for for Left,
Right, and Center. Ariana Huffington was
on that show. So, the the principal
people on the show we did we we did a
reenactment for that movie. This is
before 9/11, you know, year maybe two
two years before.
And but the hero in that movie is an FBI
agent who speaks Arabic. And and he
tries to say you can't round up every
Arab in Brooklyn
to to solve this problem. It's not done.
But it's interesting. And then the real
life hero here in in your story and in
the movie
The Report was another FBI person who at
least knew the language. These doctors
that were paid, what did you say? 100
108 million dollars.
Yeah, psychologist. Uh they didn't know
Arabic. They didn't know what they
admitted it. They didn't know anything
about the countries or culture or
anything. Right?
Not a thing.
Yeah. And yet
going to what mass media does amazingly,
this movie gave them and their torture
it justified torture.
Yes, it did. Yes, it did. And to make
matters worse when the torture report
came out, um
a big group of retired uh senior CIA
leaders, George Tenet, Jim Pavitt,
big important people, Jose Rodriguez and
Cofer Black.
They
they all attached their names to a
rebuttal.
A book that was published saying torture
worked, torture saved lives, we would do
it again if we could, we didn't make any
mistakes. It was this outrageous
Did they admit but they didn't admit it
was torture? They called it enhanced
They called it
enhanced interrogation techniques.
That's right.
Yeah. You know, I want to know, John,
how did you survive? You you lost your
pension, you served your marriage broke
up and your wife then was in the CIA.
You
all sorts of family problems. And
actually, frankly, you haven't looked
better than you do right now. You've
lost 100 lb. I don't know if I'm at
liberty to discuss this.
You look you you look like a
a sad old
bureaucratic veteran
the last couple of times I talked to you
now vigorous young man and you even have
your humor
back and some of it gallows humor. How
how the hell did you survive?
You know what, Bob? It's it's been a
process and it's taken me years.
But I have to be honest with you. I like
myself. I'm pleased with the way I
turned out.
I'm never going to be wealthy. I'm never
going to live in a giant house.
But my children respect me. I'll tell
you my my third son just started college
2 weeks ago.
And he's going to Miami University of
Ohio and he called me
I don't think we should get too specific
here.
Okay. No, that's okay.
You are a controversial
figure.
Well, he called me the other day to tell
me he was he had just walked out of his
very first philosophy course.
And um or philosophy class.
And he said, "Dad, I just walked out of
my first ever philosophy class." And I
said, "Oh, I hated philosophy. It was so
boring." And he said, "No, no, no,
listen." He said, "There are like 300
kids in the class and the professor
starts talking about um
about uh
um ethical dilemmas."
And he said, "There's this guy, John
Kiriakou. He was a loyal CIA officer and
he saw that the CIA was committing the
crime of torture. And he knew what would
happen if he went public, but he also
knew it was wrong. And so he went public
anyway." And he said, "How many of you
would have gone public?" And he said, my
my son said, "I wanted to jump up and
say, 'That's my dad.'"
And I said, "Well, I said, you know
what? Tell him tell him that uh tell him
privately that next time I'm in town to
visit you, I'm happy to talk to his
class." But that makes me proud. That
makes me happy. My children respect me.
I can sleep at night with a clean
conscience.
And you know, I I'm fine. I don't need a
new car every couple of years. I don't
need the big fancy house. I I like the
way my life turned out.
Well, except uh
you know, it's not been easy.
No.
And and and you know, I mean, the fact
of the matter is you're in a small group
of whistleblowers. I mean, so small.
It's a pathetic
Yeah.
comment on on American culture and
society because after all, if we're the
democratic society that that President
Biden celebrated uh this week in his UN
speech, if we have the special sauce and
all these other people, if they weren't
European colonialists, you know, England
and France or Germany or the whatever,
uh you know, that are also in the
Democratic mix,
but that doesn't include India now
because Modi, their leader, has
nationalist feelings, and it doesn't
include South Africa cuz they refuse
they get along with Russia. Does clearly
doesn't control influence or connect
with Russia or China. You know, so most
of Brazil sort of excludes
a majority of the world, but this
special sauce, if nothing else, I just
happened to reread
Justice Roberts' opinion on why
surveillance is bad, believe it or not.
The a Republican appointee Chief Justice
who wrote a brilliant
opinion about why the police can't crack
into your cell phone and get
information. And he quotes from the
trial of James Otis and written about
by, you know, our second
president Adams. And And he says the
American Revolution was fought over
protecting the right of the individual
to inform themselves, to speak out, to
have the sanctity of their homes. But
we've seen what whistleblowers,
you know, reach really respected people
who were at the NSA and so on. The FBI
breaks into their home, pulls them out
of the shower and everything. And you
have to really ask yourself a question,
how could a culture that prides itself
on this individualism
and free,
you know, the heroes of the free people
speak truth to power and act. We have a
handful, you know,
Daniel Ellsberg just died recently.
He gave us the Pentagon Papers. He said
he had to wait 50 years for other
whistleblowers. A document we had every
right to read, we had paid for. It was
an academic study on the basis of inside
information on how we got into Vietnam.
You You got You know, help me out here.
Yeah, Bill Binney, Kirk Wiebe, uh Tom
Drake at NSA. Uh we've got Daniel Hale
at the Air Force and Lisa Ling in at the
Air Force both in the drone program. We
have We have uh Ed Snowden from NSA and
CIA. They're the shame is, as you just
said,
even after 50 years or 50 years after
Dan Ellsberg, you can count us on two
hands. That's it.
So, that's that many. And what what you
guys knew,
thousands of people knew who were in the
government.
Oh, yes.
Uh right? How many people really I mean,
even Dianne Feinstein, we give her a lot
of credit for the report and doing it,
but she knew. And she didn't go public.
Yeah.
Sure, she did. You know, people ask me
all the time, "Well, why didn't you go
through the chain of command?"
Well, my chain of command created the
torture program and implemented the
torture program. Well, why didn't you go
to the oversight committees? Because the
oversight committees approved the
torture program and then financed it,
appropriated funds for it.
So, there were no good guys in this
scenario. The only place to go was the
media.
You know, we should explain the reason
we believe in
freedom
is not that it's a luxury. The whole
basis of the American Constitution, for
whatever its flaws, its limitations,
those wigged white guys and everything
else, we know all of the problems. But,
there was a brilliance to the insight,
which is that you have to beware of
power, that power corrupts, and that we
have a constitution that is designed uh
to prevent the very people who authored
the Constitution, when they become the
government, from exploiting their power
Yes.
over the individual, even the humblest
individual in his abode. That's why we
have a Fourth Amendment. That's why we
have the First Amendment freedom. The
idea is that's not a gift to the people.
That's a protection of freedom. That
that that that is a necessity. It's not
an indulgence, this freedom. But it is
treated as an indulgence. We'll let you
have privacy. We'll let you have free
speech when we're not at war, when there
there's no great risk, when there's no
danger,
when everything is tranquil, maybe we'll
let you have it then if you say the
right thing, if you do the right thing,
if you favor the torture program, you'll
go on MSNBC.
You'll become a star. If you oppose the
torture program, you end up in prison
like John Kiriakou. You lose everything.
You lose your pension and what have you.
And in your case, they then can turn
around and smear you cuz the only place
you could get a job and and and be able
to do what you do well, you're so well
informed, so knowledgeable, you know
more about the this area of the world,
you speak the language that's supposed
to be terrorizing us, but you have to
end up on Sputnik, a Russian
radio station that has very few
listeners because in our supposedly free
society, we cut back their access to to
people. So, you are now as just like
with Edward Snowden, oh bad guy. You
know, Snowden tried to you know, take
refuge in I think 30 different
countries. He ends up in Russia. So,
he's now a bad guy, right?
Right. Oh, you know, that's a pet peeve
of mine. People say that all the time,
"Well, Snowden defected to Russia." No,
he didn't. Snowden was in the transit
lounge of Moscow Airport on his way to
Ecuador when John Kerry canceled his US
passport and stranded him at Moscow.
a
a hero of opposition at one point to the
Vietnam War was then
Secretary of State and he canceled him.
Yeah.
And so, that's how he end up in Russia.
You know, that's so important because as
we talk about what's real news and fake
news and everything and you know, it's
so easy to blame Donald Trump for every
bit of distortion, but we've been very
good at lying. We lied about of course
to Vietnam where we lied about you know,
why the atomic bombs were dropped on
Hiroshima and Nagasaki. We lied about
lots of things and you and very
effectively so. Actually Trump is
probably one of our worst liars. You
know, he's so blatant and boorish
about it. We you know, Harry Truman was
a very effective liar. He said he never
wanted to see Oppenheimer again because
Oppenheimer did question the wisdom of
destroying mostly innocent civilians
with these bombs and so forth and
worried about it even though he helped
create it. And and so we have this weird
sense of our own history and it's
important to make
Edward Snowden a villain. What Edward
Snowden revealed to us is that private
companies which do have a right to
gather information and so forth. It's
not doesn't rise to a challenge to our
constitutionally guaranteed freedom, but
they weren't doing it privately. The US
government was invading
the machinery of of Google and Facebook
and Apple and everybody else and
grabbing the information actually
jeopardizing their position as companies
that have to have the trust of people
around the world, breaking into their
cables, breaking into general cables and
spying on the American people in clear
violation of CIA's operating rules and
and
That's right.
mandate.
And yet he's he's now the the bad guy.
Right? Because he takes refuge in the
one country where he was
trapped and and because we we didn't let
him go to Ecuador where probably he
would have been like
Julian Assange probably you know, would
have been
Oh, yeah. He would be in a He would be
in a prison in the United States now had
he actually made it to Ecuador because
there's been a change in government
there and that pro-US government turned
Julian Assange over to British
authorities and that's why he's at
Belmarsh prison.
And Julian Assange who of course was not
an American citizen was not working for
an American agency like Edward Snowden
or or John Kiriakou. He I just can't
they
the five major newspapers that published
the information I don't want to get
agitated here but you know the five
major organizations
who's the New York Times have issued a
statement saying that what Julian
Assange revealed and then they printed
was legitimate news that we had to have.
Democracy requires it. However, they
made that statement but generally shut
up about the fact that the guy who did
their journalism was a publisher like
them is has been almost driven out of
his mind
in in a prison and now we want to get
him and put him in a maximum security
prison in the United States even though
the Australian government is objecting
to that and says well wait a minute,
he's a citizen of our country. So to put
you in historical context John, I have
to say I began this by saying I admire
you as much as any anyone I've ever
interviewed
Thank you so much. That means a lot to
me Bob. Thank you so much for that.
But I've interviewed a lot of people. I
interviewed you know Bobby Kennedy and
then Jimmy Carter and you know people
all over the world and you know people
you might not like you know the Fidel
Castros or you know all sorts of people.
You know it's what I've done for a
living
but I've interviewed you a bunch of
times. I've followed every aspect of
your story and you are the great
American hero. You are. You are you know
you are the boy scout you know
who who stuck stuck to the idea which
was not
America Uber Alles but quite the
opposite you know America has to stand
for values even if the last man standing
or last woman standing believes in those
values. And and you know, how they can
That's what really got me to want to do
this interview now
because I was so shocked that my
students
that through their education and they've
gotten, you know, some of the best
access,
you know, we're top you know, top 25
school or something at USC. They're very
smart students. They want to learn.
And we had a movie, an important movie
made, the report, and I was shocked that
not one single person in my class even
knew of its existence.
You know, not one.
Amazing to me.
Yeah, and and you know, and their whole
life has been shaped by what you were
doing, right? I was in the area. They
were born then.
Mhm.
That that that's what their age is now.
They you know, this is where they're
they're 23 if they were born or 22 if
they were born that time. And and so
their whole world, our world, but their
life world has been post 9/11.
Yes.
That's it. They are the children
and it's funny, in my mind 9/11 was
practically, you know, last Tuesday.
That's how fresh it still is in my mind.
It's just crazy. Well, when you just
said at the beginning of the of the
podcast that
we're coming up on a decade ago that the
torture report was was released, I
thought, "Oh my god, how's that even
possible? A decade." But you're exactly
right. All of these all of these
students are are post 9/11
Americans.
They're the post They're the 9/11
babies.
Mhm.
That's what they are. They're 9/11
babies. So I'm there Tuesday It was
Monday, actually.
Oh, sorry. It was Wednesday. Let me be
very clear about my facts here.
Monday, yes. And I showed this movie.
You would have thought that I had just
acquired some document, you know, it's
available. You can get it on I think I
got it on Amazon Prime, you know, I was
showing it straight there. I didn't
break into any safes or anything, but
you can't read the report.
No.
You know, you can read a part of of of
it.
Uh why don't you tell let's pay tribute
to the movie.
What does it get right?
You go I don't want to send you to jail
again now.
Oh no, that's okay. Well, you know, I'm
going to make a recommendation first and
say um
that the reports out there, the
executive summary is out there. Again,
it's heavily redacted. But if you really
want to understand what it is
the investigators were trying to convey,
read the footnotes. The footnotes are so
critical to our understanding of of what
it is that the CIA was was doing. I
think the most important thing
to take from the the report, I think the
thing that Americans should be most
appalled by or most shocked by is the
fact that CIA officers
went far beyond what they were permitted
to do under the Justice Department's
terms. You know, the Justice Department
said, "You can do these 10 things and
this is how you have to do each one of
them."
And the CIA just
just tossed that off to the side and did
literally anything they wanted. We we
only learned in the report that Abu
Zubaydah, for example
was to use the CIA's terminology
rectally hydrated with hummus.
Now, doctors came out immediately and
said there is no medical benefit
whatsoever
to forcing hummus into somebody's body
rectally through a tube. They did that
to humiliate him and to torture him.
Uh there are a couple of
And, and to humiliate his culture.
Yes. Oh, yes. They threatened They
threatened to use pages of the Quran as
toilet paper.
Uh, they uh, made uh, prisoners The
prisoners, of course, were all Muslim.
They made them stand naked in front of
female soldiers.
Anything they could think of to insult
them.
Trimmed their beards.
Trimmed their beards. That's right.
That's right.
Yeah. So, it was deliberate
uh, humiliation. But, let me get back to
the critical point about the functioning
of a democracy,
which is that the truth will set you
free.
Yes, indeed.
after all, it's not uh,
okay, let's have a little democracy with
our steak.
Uh, it's nice to have. No. You The
reason we have this Constitution with
its amendments is that the founders,
again, whatever their failings, the
founders said, "We are going We have the
potential to be the bad guys."
Yes.
And if I'm not the bad guy, it'll be my
colleague over there. Or And And And
what we want to do is protect the
society against us.
Yes. Precisely.
Right.
Precisely. We're either going to be a
country
that respects the rule of law, or we're
not. It's as simple as that.
And there isn't anything in between
because you have the ability to always
be corrupted. And they knew this
because, after all, they were making a
revolution against England, which they
had admired more than any other country
in the world, most of them, right? And
And yet, now And And the English, who
they admired, would be hanging them from
the nearest tree if they lost this
revolution. And actually, quite a few
people in this country wasn't a country
yet, but in the colonies
had doubts about it, or didn't want to
do it, you know? But, this was the group
that wanted to do it, the Washington so
forth. And Washington warned us in his
farewell address after being president
for two terms about the impostures of
pretended patriotism. That's This is
what George Washington, the general,
just like General Eisenhower, warned us
about the military-industrial complex.
That's what we're talking about. We're
talking about the military-industrial
complex, the impostures of pretended
patriotism, and what they do with their
torture, with their censorship, with
their classifications is prevent the
average American citizen, or in fact the
vast, vast, vast majority of American
citizens from knowing what happened.
Knowing who are the enemy. Well, how do
they work? What do they think? That's
what a trial would do. That's what
giving journalists access would do. And
having lawyers and being able to publish
it. What was this terrorism about? Why
this ally of ours, Saudi Arabia, which
now President Biden, out of nowhere, as
we're preparing for a war with China,
which kept us alive during the pandemic,
and we don't like China cuz they're
maybe a more successful capitalist
country. Whoever's running it, really,
they're
cleaning our clock on on making stuff,
including, you know,
electric cars now crashing through the
home market. Okay, so we're going to
have a war, and in Orwellian terms, we
have to find the enemy, you know, and
Putin's the great enemy, even though
Putin is the anti-communist that our own
government backed when he was against
Gorbachev and when he was,
you know, Yeltsin's guy. So history gets
just turned. Now we want communist
Vietnam, which we once fought this
bloody, decades-long war. We want now
iPhones made in in Vietnam, communist
Vietnam, because China is communist and
they're too nationalistic, so we'll go
to Vietnam. I I if just play with
history, and what people have to
remember is this idea of freedom and
limits on power is not
an indulgence of a sane democratic
society, it's the essential oil, okay?
And that's what everybody forgets, you
know? And so
really without
spawning conspiracy theories,
we really don't know what this whole
thing was about. This war on terror and
so forth. You know, after all, if we was
really about Muslim fanaticism, we
wouldn't have gone to war with Iraq.
Everybody forgets this. I always ask
people, what did Iraq have to do with
9/11?
What? You know, not one single one of
the hijackers was from Iraq. Uh Saddam
Hussein was a a sworn enemy of Al-Qaeda.
It was the one country in the Middle
East where Al-Qaeda couldn't function
cuz Saddam Hussein was a ruthless
dictator who'd kill them. Uh
you know, anytime. So,
what we're really talking about is
information we not only have a right to
have but a need to have.
And this great adventure that happened
like now, maybe we'll end up in a
nuclear war with Russia and China then
we but we'll never know. How does this
happen?
How does this happen? Why did we all of
a sudden have big fights about Russia
with its borders and Ukraine? I mean,
everything. You we we don't get the
information.
We don't get the information. And and in
your case, let's just maybe wrap this up
with the fact of the matter is you don't
get on MSNBC, the so-called enlightened
more what? Democratic Party influenced
station. I mean, I don't know.
You know,
So, where do you get on? Sputnik and
then you're condemned for it, you know?
If you if you don't shut up and
Washington Post listened to my show and
said that I was weakening our democracy.
Oh.
And what's the reason?
Because I was criticizing a crooked
judge in Pennsylvania who took bribes to
send children to for-profit prison. He
was convicted and sentenced to 22 years.
I was I was saying it's terrible to have
crooked judges.
And the Washington Post said you were
weakening our democracy.
Yeah, I see.
Uh and
And the Washington Post, which has been
a
a conduit
for both information obtained by
whistleblowers and yet for the
government that then wants to persecute
them. I mean, the same Washington Post
that printed the Pentagon papers, but
you know, the current Washington Post
wouldn't defend
a Julian Assange
who was, as Daniel Ellsberg pointed out,
directly in line, as he pointed out
about you, as whistleblowers who were
directly in line with what he was trying
to do. You know,
I could go on a long time with you,
John. I I It is so encouraging
that you know, that they didn't get you
down.
Uh not a chance.
If they thought they that they would,
they didn't know me at all.
Well, you know, maybe we should conclude
on that. You know, how
you know,
you you're kind of a even though you
have a Greek background,
but then again, most of us in this
supposed melting pot have some other
background, but really you you're kind
of as American as apple pie.
I like to think so.
No, but I mean, just take us back. I
mean, who was John Kiriakou and how did
you end up being a truly major major
figure in American history?
Uh thank you.
uh
You know, I'm just I'm just a normal
average guy. I I grew up in Western
Pennsylvania, nuclear family. My parents
were public school teachers and uh, you
know, grew up with baseball and football
and church on Sunday and
um, my dad, when I was 8 years old, my
dad bought me a shortwave radio at an
auction for 50 cents. I still remember
it.
And that radio, that beat-up
old radio opened the entire world to me.
As soon as the sun went down, I could
listen to the BBC or Radio Moscow or
stations, you know, in in China and Cuba
and
Europe and all over the world. And I
decided then that I wanted to see the
world. I wanted to go to school in
Washington, D.C.
and I wanted to see the world. And
that's what I ended up doing.
And you saw the world and then you felt
that your fellow Americans had a right
to see parts of the
Right to know. You know, after my
whistleblowing,
uh,
a journalist who also happens to be a
psychologist, uh, told me that in his
own studies, he found that
whistleblowers have an unusually highly
defined sense of right and wrong. It's
far more highly defined than it is in
the general populace.
And he said, "It's almost like
whistleblowers can't stop themselves."
And I said, "That's how I felt." I
couldn't stop myself. I couldn't sleep
at night
knowing that this was happening in our
name.
That the government was carrying out
these crimes in our name.
So, I had to say something.
And even though they don't call it
torture and even though it is clearly
defined even in the introduction to the
report, you still have your top people,
including a former liberal congressman
Yes. Like Caneda.
Yes. You know, when I knew him, he is.
He was kind
less liberal congressman in California,
you know, but defending him.
Mhm.
The this thing and lying about what it
supposedly accomplished even though the
report destroys
even the part that we can read, the
redacted part. I want to mention
something about
Daniel Ellsberg and and his partner at
the Rand Corporation was paid for by the
Air Force and Daniel Ellsberg had been
in the Marines and been in the military
and then now was working you know, for
the government and Tony Russo, his
partner. Tony Russo, people don't know
this. I happen to
was this expert witness. I'd been to
Vietnam. I knew a lot about it. So, I
was an expert witness for Tony Russo if
it had gone to trial.
Wow.
But but because the judge
had been offered the job of being head
of FBI,
went into a mistrial at that point. But
Tony Russo turned against the Vietnam
War while he was working for the Air
Force Air Force contract evaluating the
interrogation of Vietnamese prisoners
in Vietnam.
Wow.
And he saw and recognized that they were
being tortured.
And then he saw also that they they were
not giving bad information, that it was
not in any way even justified. So,
torture was done in Vietnam and Tony
Russo who was worked with Daniel
Ellsberg to get the papers printed and
give it to the New York Times, then the
Washington Post. That's what he was
moved by. That torture aside from being
totally heinous, also was
counterproductive. I was telling the
Americans what they wanted to hear about
pursuing the war that ended up in our
most ignominious
defeat. And and so
from Daniel Ellsberg and Tony Russo to
to you, John Kiriakou, a straight line
and we have like a
I said I'd keep this a half hour, I'm
going to keep it to 1 hour.
We got 2 minutes.
I want to talk just for the last 2
minutes about Julian Assange. Yes.
Because I mean, here is a guy who did
what a journalist is supposed to do,
what a publisher is supposed to do. You
know, he wasn't in the CIA.
He hadn't taken an oath. He's not an
American. And he he found, "Hey, you're
shooting up and killing a Reuters
correspondent. You're killing innocent
civilians. You know, you're laughing
about it in your helicopter." We have
information, I'm going to reveal it. And
that guy has a We can use the word
torture. The UN has said Daniel that
Julian Assange is the UN rapporteur on
torture big report is being tortured.
And he's now the most visible victim of
of this Orwellian nightmare where
torture becomes enhanced interrogation.
You know, uh
Yes. You're absolutely right. And you
know, I
I know on on podcasts and and things
like this we try not to be specific to a
certain day, but I'm going to be
specific to a certain day. Today, six
Australian parliamentarians,
uh including four senators, two members
of the lower the lower body, the house,
including a former deputy prime minister
came to Washington. They held a rally
this afternoon at the Justice Department
and and a vigil. And they brought with
them a letter signed by 60 members of
the Australian Parliament asking
President Biden to drop the charges
against Julian Assange and let him go
home.
And I'll tell you another thing, forgive
me if I go over our 2 minutes.
I don't know if you remember the name
David Hicks.
David Hicks was an Australian national
who was was a troubled teenager. At the
age of 18, he he to Islam and then made
his way to Afghanistan to um um fight
alongside the Taliban. He ended up being
recruited into Al-Qaeda,
and because he didn't speak Arabic, uh
they just gave him a gun and told him to
stand guard at the Kandahar Al-Qaeda
training base. He happened to be in
Pakistan on 9/11, and as soon as he saw
the news, he ran back to Afghanistan to
help Al-Qaeda fight the Americans.
Okay, he was almost immediately captured
by the United States.
And we sent him to Guantanamo, where he
was tortured mercilessly.
Now, the Australian government came to
us and said, "Whoa, wait a minute. You
can't torture an Australian citizen.
This is a Five Eyes citizen. You have to
let him go."
So, we put him on trial at Guantanamo,
we found him guilty, we sentenced him to
time served, and we turned him over to
the Australians.
Well, he was a genuine bad guy.
What about Julian Assange?
Why aren't the Australians in the
streets over Julian Assange Assange?
Now, it's getting better than it was
6 months ago even.
But, more needs to be done
to to impart to the White House that
this is a This is an issue worth falling
on the sword for.
We have to release Julian Assange.
But, the government that wants to bring
him back, uh certainly the Trump
administration wanted to, but that's
that's uh Joe Biden.
Yes.
Who, by the way, voted for wars that
were based on lies.
That's right.
And so forth, you know, but now we're
all going to be encouraged to shut up
and go along with the program that we
need uh cuz there's no other old white
person we can mail, we can find. We have
to go with the one we got, otherwise all
hell will break loose, and the you know,
source of all evil, Donald Trump, will
come in and so forth. I want you to talk
finally
about good guys about uh Barack Obama.
You went You went to prison,
right? When When Barack Obama
It was Barack Obama uh the Barack Obama
administration that sent me to prison.
know. When you're president,
Yeah, you're right.
president, the buck stops with you.
I I'm trying to be nice, but you're
absolutely right.
you probably voted for the guy. I
certainly did. I got teeth shirts. I
contributed to his campaign.
I took my kids to the inauguration
with my youngest on my shoulders to see
this great this great new president who
was going to fix all of our problems.
And instead, he he makes John Brennan
uh CIA director. John Brennan, who was
the executive director of the CIA during
the torture program, was one of the
founders, the fathers of the torture
program.
And you know, Barack Obama is the one
that just allowed the drone war to
explode. In George W. Bush's last month
as president, he killed 24 people with
drones.
In Barack Obama's last month as
president, he killed 440
people with drones.
Like, is that really the country we want
to be?
What's trial by drone?
That's right.
Yeah, and and but but I wanted to make
it little personal at the end here.
You know, uh we're we're talking about
Okay, maybe we could have an argument
with with the Biden is a good guy,
but I never doubted that Barack Obama
was a good guy.
He was civil libertarian, law professor,
concerned about all these issues, talked
about limits on power, promised us he
would
not lie and would respect the
Constitution.
And here is John Kiriakou,
and your What is your crime anyway? They
claimed you gave the name of a of a of a
open member of the CIA to a news to ABC.
And really
they tried that at first. They they
said, "Oh, you gave the name of a CIA
officer to
to ABC." And I said, "He's He's never
been undercover. He's on LinkedIn as
Central Intelligence Agency."
So, it's no secret. Then they charged me
with violating the Intelligence
me just Let me just stop there because I
did follow that case. And every time you
tell me something, I then go and spend
hours Oh, wait a minute. Now, I like
John, but you know,
okay, what is he pushing here?
So, it's actually was a case where you
were asked by this reporter, as I
recall, who would Would there be someone
in the CIA who knows about all this who
disagrees with you about the torture
program? Do I have that right?
Close. Close. He asked me He sent me a
list of 12 names.
is the he we allowed
This is Matthew Cole.
He gave me a list of 12 names, and he
said, "I'm writing this book about the
rendition program. Can you introduce me
to any of these 12 people?" I said, "I
don't have any idea who these people
are."
Then he sent me another list of 12
names. And I I said, "Look, I don't know
any of these people. You clearly know
this issue better than I do." I said,
"Kidnapping wasn't my thing at the CIA.
I was always the good cop. I don't know
anything about the rendition program."
And then he said, "Well, what about the
guy that you mentioned in your book? I
think his name is John."
I said, "Oh, I said, yeah, that's John
Doe." I said, uh
"I I don't know. Whatever happened to
him, he's probably retired and living
somewhere in in Virginia."
Well, I had confirmed the last name in
the email. Now, that name was never made
public. That's why I said John Doe just
now. The name was never made public. And
after the fact,
the CIA director, um David Petraeus,
revealed the names of 10 CIA covert
operatives to his adulterous girlfriend.
He was never charged with that, but they
charged me with a felony.
And that's what I ended up going to
prison for.
So,
I'm uh we have to understand that. You
were already a controversial figure
because you had spoke as you had a right
to
Yes.
about what was wrong with the program,
right? Torture, right? So, you were
contributing to the public dialogue.
Yes.
Your crime
uh for which you end up in the prison
with I think some mafia figures you
know.
Oh, yeah, very senior mafia figures.
Yeah.
Oh, yeah.
and suddenly uh
David Petraeus, by the way, who was
somebody who's been a a professor at
different university including USC
a very distinguished The New York Times
loves him. They seem to have a profile
about him every couple of months. There
must be a a schedule of how great David
Petraeus the greatest general and all
that. And he had these black books just
just be clear about that which were for
presidential briefings that were the
most important secrets. Right? This is
not for certain.
Literally the most highly classified
information in the US government.
With these black books.
Yes.
And he let his mistress
you know, I don't want to be puritanical
here about his adulterous girlfriend or
something. That's That's you know, I'm
not interested in condemning his
personal behavior, but but his mistress
uh right? Uh did not have the clearance.
No.
Yes. So, he gave the most prized secret
current information that he was
responsible for giving to the president
of the United States. And he let his
mistress who was going to write about
this, right?
Mhm.
Right?
She was writing a biography about him.
Yeah. And so, she could read this to see
how great he was and how knowledgeable
he was, and he gets his a slap on the
wrist.
Yes, he got he ended up getting
a misdemeanor. He took a plea to a
misdemeanor count of
improper
improper Oh, improperly securing
classified information. He got 18 months
of unsupervised probation.
And at his sentencing, the judge came
down from the bench to shake his hand
and thank him for his service to the
country.
Right. Same thing the judge did with
you, right?
Right. The judge said to me, "If I could
give you 10 years, I would."
And you had actually risked your life
out there
and you know
in the center of the war on on terror.
Mhm.
And
so that double standard is what should
alarm people.
Yes.
That that you know, if they were really
stern taskmasters and you reveal class
This is what bothers me about the Trump
thing. I I am absolutely convinced that
every president who left office left
with all the documents he might need to
write his book or anything like that. I
mean, I've been I've interviewed a lot
of these people. I interviewed Richard
Nixon after his president You know, I I
I've seen Jimmy Carter before and after
his president. Ronald Reagan I talked to
very extensively as a journalist. Ronald
Reagan had no trouble at all bringing up
all sorts of things that were classified
or something. He had been president. He
got to talk about what he wanted to talk
about. I'm not going to sit here
defending Donald Trump, but my God, you
know, oh, he he he's got papers he's not
supposed to
have I mean, you know, so there's
something so annoying about the double
standard that it's okay it's okay for
Petraeus to give his mistress these
books which she was fully intending to
use. It wasn't just a "Hey, honey, read
this while I go take a shower." No, it's
you're you're writing a book. You can
read this. Top secret. You're like the
president. John Kiriakou who gives the
name of a known CIA person mentioned on
LinkedIn and so forth and you serve hard
time.
Yes.
The only one. Now, that is what the
history books have got to record. None
of the other people involved with the
torture program, none
served any time.
No, none of them. In fact, they all went
on to great riches. They all got
got
seven-figure book advances and positions
on corporate boards.
on it. Who? Who?
Oh, sure. George Tenet got 6 million for
his book. Jose Rodriguez got 4 million
for his book. And this just goes on and
on and on. They're on the boards of of
American defense contractors and
um they're talking heads. John Brennan's
a talking head on MSNBC,
you know, getting at least 100,000 just
to be on call for that. Uh they've done
very well for themselves financially.
end let's end by talking a bit about
John Brennan.
He's the guy who who threw you under the
bus, right?
Yeah, you know, I I've known John
Brennan for
30 32 33 years. And um
um never really liked him. I thought he
was over in over his head intellectually
at the CIA, but he was a political
player. He rose through the ranks. And
uh you know, I thought, well, you know,
John Brennan, I don't really have
anything to do with him. He doesn't have
anything to do with me. But then when I
was arrested and we received discovery
from the Justice Department, 15,000
pages of classified documents.
There was a memo from Brennan to
Attorney General Eric Holder
about me.
And it said, "Charge him with
espionage."
And then Holder wrote back and said, "My
people don't think he committed
espionage."
And then Brennan wrote back and said,
"Charge him anyway and make him defend
himself."
And so they did. And then they waited
until I went bankrupt and then they
dropped the espionage charges.
Here's Eric Holder who I've had dinner
with on occasion,
uh presents as a very progressive
open Well, let's let's get to the chase.
And the liberal community of Hollywood,
Eric Holder was much admired.
Uh I'm not going to drop other names,
but I I was at dinner with some very
well-known liberal people.
And here's Eric Holder who even though
he did not believe and the people
working for him did not believe you had
committed espionage, was willing, at the
head of our secret police agency, the
CIA, to charge you in the hopes of
breaking you.
Mhm.
Breaking you.
Yep.
People have got to understand this
language. We know it when the Chinese do
it, when the Saudis do it, when the
Russians do it. We say, "Oh, yeah, yeah,
that's totalitarian. They break them.
They destroy them." You know,
uh what are we trying to do with Julian
Assange?
Yeah.
Drive him crazy.
Sure.
You know, uh
Make him kill himself.
Yes.
So they don't have to worry about it
anymore.
And that's what they tried to do with
you. Here's so here's John Brennan, the
darling of MSNBC,
uh which you know, we have
one monopoly corporation owned thing.
That's the bad guys. That's Fox and then
there's this is the liberal one. And
this guy is telling uh
the Justice Department to charge you,
right?
Right.
Right. There's supposed to be separation
of these agencies. Justice Department is
supposed to be interested in justice.
The CIA is supposed to be, you know, a
spy agency that we're watching very
carefully so they don't overstep and
they're not supposed to be be spying on
Americans.
Yeah, and then you know, in the end, and
I mean the very end, the Justice
Department made their final final offer.
Best and final offer, they said. Now, I
was facing 45 years, they offered 10,
then eight, then five, then three and a
half, then two and a half. And my lead
attorney said, "You know, I've been a
lawyer here for 52 years, and I've never
seen them come down in time. Usually, if
they offer you 10 and you say no, then
they offer you 12, then 15, then 18."
And I said, "Well, why are they going
down in time?"
He said, "Because they have a [__] case
and they know it's shit."
He said, "We're going to go to trial."
Well, I believed we were going to go to
trial because I believed I hadn't done
anything wrong. And so they make their
best and final offer of two and a half
years
uh in prison, and my my wife and I
stayed up all night to talk about it,
and we decided I'm going to turn it
down.
And so I emailed the attorneys at like
6:00 in the morning. I said, "I I've
decided I'm going to turn it down. Let's
go to trial. Once I get in front of a
jury, they're going to see how
ridiculous this is, and I'm going to
win."
The attorneys drove to my house and got
there at 7:00 in the morning. I put on a
pot of coffee.
The lead attorney was very blunt. He
said
He said, "You stupid son of a [__]
take the deal."
And
the attorney who I liked and respected
the most
got right in my face, and he said, "You
know what your problem is? Your problem
is you think this is about justice, and
it's not about justice. It's about
mitigating damage. Take the deal."
And then the third attorney, who was
really very much a southern gentleman,
um said, "If you were my own brother, I
would beg you to take this deal." And I
said, "Well, listen, realistically,
let's say I don't take the deal, I go to
trial, and I'm convicted. Realistically,
what am I looking at?" And he said, "12
to 18 years. Take the deal."
And so, I took the deal.
So, just for people who have not
followed your case, and for that, I
blame the mass media, and I blame
politicians of the right and left and
Republican and Democrat, and I blame
Barack Obama. Let's lay it out there.
too.
Yeah. I just Barack Obama will put you
through this ordeal. Uh
and a lot of other people that
someone like myself uh probably met at
different receptions and interviews and
so forth, as I did with Eric Holder.
Uh but, I just want people to understand
the power, the power of the state, the
power of government.
And And I saw it with Daniel Ellsberg
and Tony Russo, because I say I was a
I've been involved in that trial. And
And Daniel Ellsberg, a
literally a Boy Scout Marine, gung-ho,
pro-Vietnam War at the beginning, you
know, blah, blah, and everything,
suddenly up against, "Hey, this guy
Nixon, President Nixon, he can put me
away for 140 years or so." I forget the
exact
Yeah, that's that's what it was.
Right. And he never did get that trial.
He probably would have lost it, you
know. And uh
uh and and so, you're in this position
where you're
you still believe
that this is a fair You are still naive
enough to believe
that you could turn down an an offer to
I did in in October of 2012.
Yeah. I I believed it.
But, now I'm I'm a realist now.
No, the I would the whole system is
rigged.
this would be a good way to end Well,
who is John Kiriakou? I don't have this
the skill set to write a great movie
about you.
Uh but, you really are I I just put it
right out there. I think unquestionably
one of the great American
stories.
Thank you.
And I would like to get inside your
mind. We have a few We can take as much
time we want. Hell, they're not going to
send us to jail, I don't think. So,
uh
but but seriously,
uh what's going through your mind? You
know what?
You know, six What did they say? 14
years in jail? 16 years? What were you
Uh yeah, 12 to 18 he told me to expect.
they stuck to their word, they could
have gone for more. I mean, you know,
look at Julian Assange. I mean, how many
is he facing? Uh
Oh, like 100 and something.
Yeah, yeah. And what did he do? He He
revealed an embarrassing, deeply
embarrassing story casting our military
in a bad light.
Yes.
So,
uh
in your case,
just take us the the Boy Scout,
you know,
uh
it's Mr. Smith Goes to Washington. And
this is
you you you still believed
Mhm.
you you still believed
I did. I believed in the system. I don't
at all anymore.
Not at all.
And it to tell you the truth, it it got
even worse under Trump.
You know, this is this is not a partisan
issue.
Both parties are are equally uh
you know, culpable
in this this assault on our civil
liberties.
Um
you know, uh
pardons were for sale, for example,
under Trump.
Uh
Trump is celebrating WikiLeaks during
the campaign and then and then actually
files charges against Julian Assange.
And then Joe Biden has the opportunity
to drop the case against Julian Assange
and he picks up the Trump case and keeps
it going.
It's just not fair.
Yeah, it's it's
it's startling. Um
Okay, well, I don't know where to I
guess we'll just end it, but uh
I don't I wouldn't have your courage.
Uh
Oh, I find that hard to believe.
No, no, come on. I look, I've I I'm I'm
not a veteran of imprisonment. I've been
in
a few jails for a couple of nights here
and they actually wasn't jailed even
uh in Lithuania, Russia, Soviet Union
and I
and uh I was in China during the
Cultural Revolution being lectured to.
That was pretty scary. I've been I've
been around Algeria, a few things, but
those were all a few days here, a few
days, scary. Uh but, you know, really
for you and then you you know,
uh you're still relatively young, you
got young kids and everything and you
could take a deal. I probably would have
taken the first deal. Okay, what was
that? 20 years? 10. 10? Okay, I probably
would have said steal and maybe they'll
give me a break, maybe they'll I'll get
parole or something. You know, really,
uh and to have that naivete that you
actually thought I think it's absurd to
think you would have won your trial.
Yeah, it is absurd.
Yeah.
It is absurd.
Yeah, just cuz you happen to be telling
the truth.
Yeah.
It doesn't make any difference.
No. Yeah.
I didn't have a chance. I didn't have a
prayer to win that trial.
Right. And and and
And the lawyers knew it.
I want people to understand this. I
mean, first of all, the great thing is
we have, you know, we can search
everything. I tell my students, you
don't have to believe a word I said. Go
out there after class in a half hour you
could find out if I'm full of it. And
you know, that's the great thing about
the internet. You can find a lot of bad
information, but you certainly want to
see whether this is a lot of crap,
whether your professor's lying to you.
Go. If it takes you a half an hour, so
it'll take you an hour, you know, two
hours. You got time. Okay. So, anybody
can check out John Kiriakou. They can
begin by listening to some of our
podcasts that I have that are here on
KCRW.
It's still up there, but you know,
they can check it out. You've written a
couple of books
that are available and so forth. And and
they will encounter smears. Oh, the
guy's a Putin agent or he's on Sputnik
or Yeah, yeah. Okay, but but people are
learning to cut through
the bull. I I I can tell you that. Like
my students, they're suspicious as they
should be of me from day one. Yes, this
guy did this, but I also read a critical
article. I also saw that So,
that's the positive thing about the
internet. We people are are developing
their own [__] detectors.
And and yeah,
and you can get to the bottom of it. So,
I invite anybody listening to this
Let's just assume Shears you know, being
paid off by this guy or something or by
the Putin or whatever. Let's go check it
out. Let's go check it out, you know?
And there's a lot to check out here.
Let's check out, you know, what did they
learn about the
war on terror? And what about Zero Dark
Thirty? And go watch this I you know,
first of all, what's the other thing you
said they should read? I want to put
that up there.
The introduction
The the the executive The executive
summary.
Yeah. I'm going to try I'm going to try
to post that. And that's that's readily
available even if it's heavily redacted
form.
You can still get a sense of what they
they were trying to impart.
Right. And then
and watch the movie The Report. It's one
of the best things that's come out of
Hollywood. And unfortunately, as I
learned, that's why we're doing this
today, I was shocked that a very smart,
large group of students had never even
heard of it. It's not part of the
culture. There's no accountability. And
these these zealots from the CIA and
others who lied to us and everything,
they're honored by being on what is
supposed to be the more progressive mass
media outlet of MSNBC. You know, how
many times have you been invited to be
on MSNBC?
It's been a very long time. The last
time I was on MSNBC was with Daniel
Ellsberg and I'm going to say it was
probably
six years ago.
It's been a long time.
So, oh, there it is. People got to have
their own, you know, editorial page and
their own guidance and so forth. But I I
just really believe In fact, the most
chilling thing I learned from today
because you reminded me
when you say explain what your crime is.
Let's Let's end on that.
You what When you say what what was your
crime? Why How could they And the
Justice Department was right. What is
the crime? Where is the espionage? What
What What?
You know, why did Barack Obama he must
have spent 20 minutes looking at your
record?
Did anybody ever say what what was
Barack Obama thinking? You were not You
were well known. You were well known.
We were told um by uh an attorney at the
National Security Council that Obama had
a Nixonian obsession with national
security leaks.
And uh
he was perfectly happy to come down on
me like a ton of bricks, not because it
was me, not because of what I had done,
but because he wanted to scare anybody
else who might be thinking about going
to the press with classified
information.
Okay. That may be the most important
revelation of this right now hour and 24
minutes
uh interview that I promised we would
keep to 30 minutes, but I still have my
Obama t-shirts. I believe I paid $200 a
piece for them. Famous artists not
originals but copy. I remember I bought
it from a bundler. Uh I went to a dinner
in San Diego. I was speaking to the ACLU
and they sat me next to a woman who was
a bundler for Obama
and I said it's in the bag and she said,
"No, we really need money." And I wrote
a check for $500 or $600 I think for two
or three t-shirts which I didn't have.
Had to go kind of check to do that the
next day. But anyway, you know, you're
telling me something about Obama
that I really didn't know until this
moment.
And tell me what you learned and how you
learned it and I mean to think of I mean
here is the constitutional law
professor.
Right.
And you know, I I should say I
interviewed Nixon after he was president
some length and he wrote some good books
and Nixon was pretty complex person.
I'll I'll give you that. But Nixonian is
about as bad as it gets. Nixonian's
vindictive
Well, remember
That's the heart of the story.
From the enactment of the Espionage Act
in 1917
until Barack Obama was elected
president, three Americans were charged
with espionage for uh speaking to the
press.
Just in the eight years of the Obama
presidency, eight people eight
whistleblowers were charged with
espionage for speaking to the press.
That's almost three times the number of
all previous presidents combined.
That really
encapsulates it for me.
This wasn't an accident or a one-off.
This was a policy.
Who were the eight?
Uh let's see.
Tom Drake, Chelsea Manning
No, let let's go slow.
Well, I'm going to have to Google it now
cuz I can't remember them all off the
top of my head.
the ones you can remember. Tom Drake was
a highly respected employee of the
National Security Agency, right?
Yes.
And he did go to congressional
committees with this information.
Yes.
Right.
Well, he did go to the congressional
committees with with his information.
And um
and uh they arrested the congressional
staff member.
On top of arresting Tom Drake. So, let's
see. There's Tom Drake.
There is Shamai Leibowitz from the FBI.
Uh Bradley Chelsea Manning.
Stephen Kim from the State Department.
Jeffrey Sterling from the CIA.
John Kiriakou from the CIA.
Let me see see
who else is here. That's six.
Did I say Ed Snowden?
No.
Okay, Ed Snowden. Oh, and here's the
other one. Uh Don Shackle Shackleford
from the Navy.
Yeah, Drake, Leibowitz, Kim, Manning,
Shackleford, Sterling, Kiriakou, and
Snowden.
And their crime
was
speaking to the press.
And that's called espionage.
Right.
are they telling the press?
This is worth noting.
Yeah.
This is worth the This should be on the
midterm.
Really, this is worth noting. What is
the crime of these eight people that
Barack Obama, an enlightened
constitutional law professor, who for
many Americans and certainly for me for
for quite a long time, we thought was
really the most principled guy we'd had
run for president
Yeah.
and win.
Yeah, we all believed that.
Well, at least a lot of us. So, what was
the crime of the eight people that he
brought Espionage charges compared to
the three by all the presidents before
him and ever since the act was passed?
Yeah.
Well, it was revealing things like
warrantless wiretapping. That was a lot
of it.
Uh torture.
Uh war crimes in Iraq.
Um politicized analysis on North Korea.
Um the FBI wiretapping Americans uh
without uh court approval.
You know all about the Snowden
revelations, of course, which confirmed
everything that Tom Drake had told us.
Um
Yeah, and then and then later on, I
mean, under Trump, you have to add uh
Daniel Hale, the drone whistleblower,
who ended up with 46 months uh in a
federal uh prison for for telling the
press that
that we more often than not we kill uh
civilians, women, children, elderly
people instead of the uh intended target
of these drone attacks.
So, it continues.
Information we have not only a right but
a need
to know if we're going to be citizens,
if we're going to be a democratic
society. All right, John Kiriakou, uh
I love it when you take us to school and
uh you do it.
Oh, I love doing this.
Yeah, but I mean, the idea that you have
been not been crushed,
that
you know, that that the bastards
couldn't let them to you.
No way. give bastards a bad name, but I
mean Uh
you know, I
I uh
I have same kind of origin myself
technically, but you know, so I've
always offended using that word, but
that slogan, don't let the bastards get
you down.
Yes.
Really really applies to you.
It is really quite
you know, I don't want to be gushing
here or anything, but you know, I
interview a lot of people and frankly I
go back to like the first time I
interviewed you and I thought, man, this
guy's going to be a head case
in no time. Really, I just couldn't
imagine it. I couldn't imagine what
you're up against. I don't
I I could have gone that way. I could
have gone that way.
Yeah, and then you had some really bad
encounters, car crashes, things
happening.
Oh yeah.
Yeah, and uh you know, they really tried
to destroy your life and you know, hey
you haven't looked better in all the
time that I've talked to you, so
Thank you very much.
leave it at that.
Good to see you.
Yeah, and I want to thank uh Laura Condi
Rajian and Christopher Ho at KCRW for
posting these shows. We've been doing it
for I guess about 6 years now. Joshua
Sheer has been our executive producer
all that time. Diego Ramos who writes
the introduction, Max Jones who puts up
the video, and the JKW Foundation in
memory of the late Jean Stein, a
terrific and fiercely independent uh
writer
uh who puts up some funding for this.
So, till next week with another edition
of Shear Intelligence, that's it. And
thank you, John, so much.
Thank you.
Yeah.